Okay, I'm back with Dylan Patel, founder
of semi analysis. Our version of a
family Thanksgiving dinner is a regular
yearly podcast, but you're not actually
related. We'll tell the people this.
[laughter]
It'll destroy the myth. Um, walk me
through. So, basically where the world
economy is headed is more and more
becoming a function of where like lab
economics are headed, where like the
comput is headed, etc. So, I want to
understand where the crazy future ends
up within a few years. But uh let's
start with just where we are today. So
walk me through lab compute and lab
revenue right now and then be projecting
out a year or two.
>> Yeah. So when we go back to last year,
even at the end of the year, most of GDP
growth in America was just AI
infrastructure. And as we look towards
this year, about a third of the compute
coming online is for the labs for open
eye. Now it may be built by others and
then rented to them but it's in at the
end customer it's them. Um as we go
forward into the future the the numbers
for computer ballooning right we're at
you know you know a little bit over a
trillion dollars of capex this year as
we go out into 2018 it's going to be
more than $2 trillion. Um the labs are
also taking an increasing percentage of
this. And so ultimately you've got a
very interesting situation where the
labs are going from companies that
spend, you know, tens of billions of
dollars a year to hundreds of billions
of dollars a year to forecasting to
spend trillions of dollars a year even
um at towards the end of the decade. And
this is at least some of the contracts
they've begun signing with their
partners. And so this requires a big
reshaping of what happens with their um
economics, right? you know, so up until
now, there have been companies that
mostly lost money. Um, Anthropic started
turning a profit in Q2. Um, it's
believed at some point in Q3, OpenAI
could potentially start turning a profit
even. Um, with the big rise of Codeex
and and 5.6 and all this. Um, but if we
go back a year ago, everything that they
all the money they had was venture
funded losses, right? If we go back to
even the beginning of this year was
venture funded losses. um they they've
now turned the corner and are actually
starting to profit. Now, that doesn't
mean they're not taking in new capital.
The new capital is still coming in to
accelerate the growth further, but
ultimately there's more and more of
their business is being funded off of
their own revenue rather than capital
injections into them. Over the last, you
know, year and a half, their margins
have really skyrocketed. You know, the
the base cost of compute tends to be
around 10 or 13 or 15 million per
megawatt. The most interesting aspect
about what's happening now is before
again they were generating if they
served a model right GPT4 being served
on um you know Nvidia hopper GPUs was
generating negative gross margin for
open AAI but now when openai serves GPD
5.6
or anthropic serves, meet Opus 5 or
Mythos uh Fable 5, their revenue
generation has passed well beyond the
sort of incremental 10 $15 million per
megawatt. In the case of Anthropic, the
the revenue has gone as high as 50 uh
million per megawatt. Um and and what
that now enables them to do is hey if I
spend 10 bucks on inference capacity
actually generate 50 bucks of revenue
and then I can turn around and
incrementally spend all of that profit
on training.
>> One thing I'm very interested in
understanding is how you see the
centralization of compute happening at
the labs or the relative ratio of
compute that goes to the world versus
goes to the labs. um where if you say
right now a third of marginal compute is
going to the labs by when is it over
half of the incremental comput in the
world is going to the labs and by what
point do the labs have basically a vast
majority of the world's compute
>> yeah so so earlier this year you know
the beginning of this year anthropic
openi started at two for openai and less
than two for anthropic um end of this
year they're both above five um so
they've three 4x compute as a
Um when you when you look at the
incremental compute added that's about
30% of the compute added this year and
as we step forward to next year given
what's already been signed and penned
and inked you've got something even more
dramatic right you've got anthropic open
AI are taking uh as much as 40 to 50% of
compute uh next year and the
centralization doesn't look like it's
slowing down or stopping in fact it
looks like it's only accelerating now
who's building that compute for them
will change. Um, you know, next year a
big new entrance is for example, SpaceX
is building a ton of compute and they're
actively going to lease quite a bit of
it to Anthropic and OpenAI most likely
because they're the ones who can who
have the marginal capability to pay the
highest price. In addition, OpenA and
Enthropic are also starting to build
their own compute. OpenAI with their own
chips, Anthropic with TPUs that they're
purchasing with from Google and
deploying with Fluid Stack. And so when
you ask, hey, when does half of the
world's incremental new compute go to
just open anthropic?
>> I mean, it's it's really by the end of
next year,
>> it's already half of the incremental
compute is going to entropic and open
>> because uh comput is growing so fast
>> incremental compute is going to be
basically most of compute. So it's very
soon you're saying maybe within a year
and a half or two years and most of the
world's compute is owned by two labs or
at least is serving the demand from two
labs. Um, how long do you think? So,
there's this trend where maybe world
compute in gigawatts doubles every year,
but the compute at the frontier laps
triples every single year. But if you
keep the current trend going, it goes
from like two at the beginning of this
year to close to like six at the end of
this year to just multiplying out by
three, 18 by the end of 2027, 54 by the
end of 2028.
Are you like, okay, at that point they
simply can't continue tripling given the
amount of world compute or how how do
you see the world compute situation over
the next few years? Yeah. So if the
incremental compute adds this year 30
gawatt, next year 50 gawatts and the
year after that 70 roughly, you end up
with this really interesting phenomenon
which is okay well a new watt deployed
this year significantly more efficient
than the watts deployed 2 years ago. So
actually you know a humongous percentage
of the world's compute was deployed this
year even though it didn't double the
number of watts deployed. I'm deploying
GB300s and TPUv7s and tranium 3s which
are way way way more efficient. you
know, 3x 5x more performance per watt
than the prior generation chips. And so
ultimately, you've got a huge um ladder
here. So if Enthropic and OpenAI take
on, you know, 45% of compute next year,
you've you've got them in, let's say,
December 27, they have taken on half of
the world's incremental new compute, but
that half of the world's new incremental
compute is actually at a higher
performance than everything else before
it. So you've got another multiplier on
that. So, by the time you're in like
towards the end of 2028, if this trend
continues, which I see nothing that's
stopping it, um you you've got them just
controlling most of the usable, you
know, flops in the world on their own.
>> The thing I'm confused about is why you
think we only add 80 gawatt in 2028 if
we entered a world in which the price
the value of comput increases so much.
>> That's the upper bound, by the way.
That's the that's the like I'm so
bullish,
>> right? Okay. So le let's let's do some
train of thought here. So when I
interviewed you a few months ago, you
said in order to make a gigawatt of I
think Vera Rubins, you need one sec. You
need 55,000 N3 wafers, 6K N5 wafers, and
170K DRAM wafers. Um I don't know those
numbers.
>> I'm going to troll you, but the way you
said wafers was so wafers.
[laughter]
By the way, when we first uh when we
first moved to the US, I had the the VW
thing pretty bad and I was a vegetarian.
>> Vegetarian. I remember you told me about
this [laughter]
>> in North Dakota. I was in elementary
school and I'd be like,
>> "Can I get a wedgie?
>> Can I get some wedges?" [laughter]
>> Anyways, so that's for one gigawatt,
right? Yeah. Yeah. Now I had an LLM run
your wafer fab equipment model and
figure out how much um tooling how much
the tooling cost to produce a gigawatt
of compute basically every single year
and we said had like three to four
billion. Now suppose you add in you know
clean rooms and uh shell and everything
else at the fab. So $6 billion of like
fab capex produces every single year a
gigawatt and a gigawatt produces right
now a hundred billion dollars of revenue
but also that 6 billion in capex is
producing a gigawatt every single year
and that gigawatt is producing hundred
billion every single year. So even over
the course of five years so you know
the first gigawatt has generated five
years of profits the second gigawatt
that the fab has produces generated four
years of profits and so on. Um 6 billion
of capex at the fab level will have
generated over a trillion dollars of end
re end AI revenue.
>> Yeah there's a lot of opex along the
way. There's a lot of um other capbacks
like the data center, the power
>> and you have to pay like you know the
open for there's a lot of different
people who need money here.
>> So but
take away half of it for all this all
these middlemen. The thing is there's a
100x discrepancy between fab capex and
end revenue generated. More than that
actually really but uh we're just being
very conservative. And as a result, this
is capitalism, right? Like you would
imagine that people are going to figure
out like we're going to be you're you
have this huge discrepancy where you can
turn $1 into $100 and you're they're not
going to figure out a way to make more
mirrors.
>> I mean, they are. It's just these
mirrors take some time to bake, right?
>> But the emergency are so big. were like
anthropic and open air like we could
make a trillion dollars right now but
we're just bottlenecked on the mirrors
that go into the ASML machines like
they'd spend okay how can we make more
mirrors if we spend hundred billion
dollars on this right that's a situation
we're going to be in pretty soon and I'm
just like we're not going to be able to
solve that supply constraint that just
seems quite hard to imagine
>> no there's definitely um you you you've
seen people do funny arbitragees here
where they buy like turbines and then
they try and resell them because the
value of a turbine is way more because
it's the thing bottlenecking
$400 million conceion
dollars, right? But but ultimately like
yes, capitalism will cause these things
to expand, but it's it's a whip, right?
It takes a long time for the whip signal
to get to the tail end um of of that.
And so the supply chain doesn't react
immediately. In fact, you go to talk to
to someone at Carl's Ice, they're like,
"Yeah, yeah, yeah. We need to make a
hundred EUV tools by the end of the
decade." I think when we first had our
when we had our episode earlier this
year, they didn't even think they needed
to make that many enough mirrors to make
100 EUV tools a year. Um, and and so now
they're they've like sort of they're
like, "Okay, we need to do that." But in
reality, you know, because of all the
economics of what's going on, it it
should be even more. Um, but it takes so
long to to
>> suppose they every single company in the
firm, sorry, in the stack got private
equityed
>> like somebody came in who was super hi
pill and was like we're going to
maximize production. How fast what do
you think the physical constraints on
making more things would be
>> because we're the reason I ask is we're
phys pretty soon going to be in a world
where the lab revenue or just AI cash
flows because obviously the accelerators
also have these huge cash flows will be
so big that you can just fund extreme
expansion of all this production from
cash flows themselves.
>> Yeah, I I I do agree generally there's
obviously some physical constraints. Um,
the way the supply chain is expanding
currently, the 100 is roughly still the
right number
>> for 2030.
>> 100 ASML tools
>> for 2030, but you know, if you said,
Carl's ice, here's $10 billion, please
just expand production, that
would change things. And you would have
to do this with every company in the
supply chain. I don't think it'll happen
this year. I don't think it'll happen
next year. I don't have I don't think
it'll happen the year after because the
world is capital constrained. But in a
world where say the top labs are
generating let's say even combined a
trillion dollars in revenue next year
they're not able to say 10
>> I don't think they're going to do that
but
>> yeah or hundreds of billions at least
right it seems like and they realize
where the world is headed
>> I feel like they could just make
>> so so the thing is the labs can spend
hundreds of billion they're going to
generate hundreds of billions of revenue
next year but ultimately capex next year
is like $2 trillion so you've got this
big mismatch right um you know the the
wafer fabrication equipment supply chain
will do, you know, two, you know,
something on the order of $200 billion.
The data center market supply chain will
do even more. The accelerator supply
chain will do even more. You know, the
energy supply chain will do a number.
You know, you you sum all this up, it's
going to be, you know, well north of $2
trillion of capex. So, the labs have not
yet gotten to the point where their cash
flows can fund this stuff.
>> Of course. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
obviously, they will like never get to
that point, right? because they want to
keep reinst
um yeah if the current catch continues
would be like north of 50 gigawatts per
lab by the end of 2028. So between them
they'd have 100 gigawatts. Um those
gigawatts as you're saying drive
manyfold more throughput or more
performance by 2028 than they are now
right because the hardware has gotten
better. So not only have like flops for
watt increase but also the hardware gets
better at
um working with AI workloads. Okay. So
100 gawatt for the labs end of 2028. How
much is like world compute? I think that
may be a little difficult given 2028 you
start to have they've taken 70 80% of
incremental compute and I'm not sure
what happens to markets then right you
know how much does the price of compute
skyrocket for them to actually be able
to buy 70 80% of compute
>> is you know Google or Meta or Amazon
willing to sell even that much um also
one caveat when we're sort of talking
about these gigawatt numbers is you know
when Amazon is serving bedrock anthropic
models
that counts as enthropic compute in sort
of our worldview because it is
effectively at the end of the day
counted as revenue for Enthropic.
>> Um even though like there's a revenue
share and credit back and all that. Um
but ultimately
>> in 2028 it's it's you know if they get
to 100 gigawatts combined they have done
really disruptive things to the market
because anyone can make money off of 10
to 15 million per megawatt compute
today. You literally like I kid you not
it's not that hard. Go get a GB300 rack.
Go download the Kimmy Weights. Go
download VLM or SGlang. Set it up. You
know, Codex and Fable can actually help
you do this. It's pretty simple. I mean,
it's not like it's, you know, it's not
trivial, but it's not like rocket
science. And go put it on open router.
It's very simple. Um, and and you'll
start generating more revenue than
you're paying for the compute. Um, and
so this is this has sort of already led
to this compute pricing 10 to$15 million
per megawatt start to inflect up. Um,
and to get to that 100 gawatts in 2028,
you have to believe that the labs can
outpay for compute because anyone can
make money at 10 to 15, you you know,
does compute now get to $25 million a
megawatt? Does it get to $40 million a
megawatt?
>> But as you're saying, it's already the
case that the labs are generating way
more revenue per megawatt than everybody
else. If they stay as far ahead as they
are currently, you'd expect that to be
the continue the case. If there's like
some kind of recursive self-improvement,
where the AI labs are like relatively
uplifted, where they have models
internally they're not releasing
externally that are helping them make
the next model better, you'd expect that
to be even more the case. And aren't you
already seeing this where like SpaceX or
whoever's like slightly further behind,
we'll just sell compute to the highest
bidder. If they can't internally
monetize it as well as the labs, so I
feel like it's continue expecting them
to be able to gobble up like bid for
larger and larger shares of the comput.
I think that is my worldview that they
will continue to gobble up more of the
compute, but ultimately they can't do it
at at current pricing or anywhere close
to it.
>> Sure. Sure.
>> They they do have to start paying 25 30
50 million a megawatt to really gobble
up 70% of the world's compute in 2028 to
get to that 100 gawatts by 2028, which
is a very sort of aggressive goal. The
other aspect of this that's really
challenging is we've already seen a huge
slowdown for the AI labs, right? this
this regulation that they advocate for
is actually slowing down the labs a lot
more than it slows down you know sort of
the open source Chinese language models.
Um you know OpenAI not releasing uh
Astra OpenAI stopping training for two
weeks. Anthropic not releasing what
their safety assessment said is model 2
which is widely believed to be the next
version of Mythos. they're clearly not
releasing their best models and in which
case their revenue per megawatt stalls
or even can start to decline again
because other models are competitive
again. Um so it's not that they're
falling behind, it's just that they're
not releasing their best stuff.
>> What if there is some regulatory impact
that prevents them from releasing their
best models now? Their revenue per
megawatt does not climb as fast. Then
their ability to buy that incremental
compute for a higher price than everyone
else starts to diminish. and then maybe
they can't get to that 100 gigawatts is
is sort of in in a world where safety
doesn't matter. I I do believe that's
exactly what happens, right? They can
start generating $100 million per
megawatt or more and they can pay $50
million a megawatt and no one else has
any logical reason to do anything with
their compute besides say please Daario
take everything off of my hands. Um but
there are you know forces at play uh
that which we cannot describe u that
that would potentially slow this down.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean I think an good
intuition pump is just how what if the
AI models were literally as good as a
fully automated software engineer.
They're not currently there yet, right?
Like I think they're far from just being
able to fully automate the job of like a
full white collar worker. But white
collar workers earn, you know, six
figures or north of that a year. Um and
if you have a gigawatt that can sustain
a population of like say a million of
white collar workers just let's say
roughly right. Um that's like you could
then off the back of that
that would be 100 billion. That's
actually surprisingly low. [laughter]
>> Yeah. 100k per person million
population. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um
>> I don't know but it' be many hundreds of
billions of dollars if you get like full
AGI uh per
>> I think the other aspect of this is and
we've continued to see this the most of
the value capture is not happening right
like most of the value that these models
generate does not get given to open
anthropic u thankfully so far it is
mostly just being given to the users
right Jane Street with their exclusive
contract with openai for GP5.6 six ultra
fast mode or Jane Street where they're
like one of Anthropic's biggest
customers is generating way way way way
more value out of the tokens they're
paying for than Anthropic is uh
generating in terms of profit, right?
Because they get to, you know,
>> make money off of the
>> market. Um or Meta, who at one point
was, you know, rumored to be, you know,
as much as 10% of Anthropic's business.
um you know, [clears throat] they're
generating way more efficiencies by
optimizing their ad algorithms or what
have you and and getting engagement time
5% longer and you know, all these
things. They're they're making way more
money off of using these models than
than anthropic. And so the ultimately,
you know, and that's that's what's
required. So sure, if you had a million
new software engineers, the cost per
software engineer would also fall.
>> One thing I'm confused about is does the
market come into equilibrium? And if it
comes into equilibrium, would you just
expect the price of compute to equal
whatever enthropic and OpenAI can
generate from it or be very close to it
with like a small amount of markup for
Anthropic and Open AAI? Like right now,
it's really weird that there's a 4x or
more difference between what compute
sells for and how much money anthropic
can make from it. And in a world where
the revenue per gigawatt continues to
increase if Anthropic's ability to
monetize a gigawatt doubles or triples
or something, it'd be weird if then the
gap continued to increase. And so
Enthropic just by like having some
software having some weights can take
something that cost them $10 and then
turn it turn into $100.
>> Yeah. So there's there's a bit of um
this is always a fun question, right?
Which is where does the value go in AI?
AI is generating all this value. You've
got, you know, the end user, which we I
think we all agree is generating more
value than anyone else. Hence, they're
paying a lot for these models. But then
you have, you know, the app layer. Well,
so far the app layer has generated very
little value. Um, then you've got the
model layer, which again up until a year
ago was generating negative gross
margins and is now generating massive
positive gross margins. Um, and looks
like it's on the path to generating, you
know, hund00 million per megawatt. Um,
so turning, you know, $105 into $100, as
you said. Um but if we go back again a
year ago, the hardware supply chain was
generating all this gross margin while
literally everyone else was losing money
on it. Um open anthropic were just
plowing VC money in. Um and and as were
many other startups and and many of
these hyperscalers are building
infrastructure without knowing if there
was going to be a payoff. Um so
ultimately you had this like you know
negative value being created on the
model layer almost if you will um
because they were selling the tokens for
less than it cost them on the infra side
and all the values being created used at
the chip the fab initially in 2023 the
memory guys were making no money off of
you know HPM or memory for AI even
though theoretically their value they
were delivering was humongous. Now
you've got well actually KSMC makes way
less value than the memory guys. um is
that actually how much you know they're
capturing less value even though so so
the the value capture is shifted around
a lot which is very fun for um people
tracking the market or participating in
the market like like Jane Street as an
example [laughter]
>> you got to plug them that hard
[laughter]
>> um so you know what happens you know
going forward does anthropic and openi
you know they've they've they've slowly
started a balloon in value capture do
they balloon and take all the value
capture well that was the thought and
then and then Elon showed actually no, I
can sell my compute for $25 million a
megawatt or $40 million a megawatt to
Enthropic and Google. Um, even if it's a
[clears throat] short-term thing, I've
sold it for this price and I'll recoup
my entire capex in a year.
>> So, what's your prediction of how much
the relevant Toronto compute like B300s
or whatever that sold for 40b a gigawatt
the SpaceX sold for 40b a gawatt to
Google? What does that sell for at the
end of next year? I think most compute
will still continue to transact at sub20
$20 billion a gigawatt
>> even at the end of next year
>> because all of it has to be financed for
compute that you can build without
financing right if if Meta can build
compute Microsoft Amazon SpaceX can
build compute without finding a customer
just saying it I'm going to build
this compute
>> and then turn around and wait till it's
already built they now control what's
going on so so most compute is
contracted well before it's built
>> and so this is sort of what Elon took
advantage of in market is. He actually
had all this compute and he was like,
"Hey, Anthropic, I know you're making
like 60 plus billion dollars per
gigawatt. Why don't you just buy my
stuff for a crazy amount of money?" And
obviously, you know, it's not like Elon
decided this or Anthropic decided this.
It sort of markets figured itself out.
Um, other people, you know, you go to a
random cloud, they're like, "Okay, I'm
going to build a gigawatt of compute or
100 megawatts of compute. I'm going to
spend the capex. I need to turn around
and find a customer. If I want to find a
customer, I need to find the capital.
Who's going to give me the capital? And
the customer the customer has to sign a
deal. And then I take the customer's
commitment to the credit markets and I
raise the capital. And so there's this
sort of like completely different power
structure where Meta who is effectively
hoarding compute. Them and SpaceX are
plausibly the like number three. And the
only plausible number three is because
they're hoarding all this compute.
They're using their balance sheets and
capabilities to build compute to build
compute without an end customer that's
monetizing it at a huge degree. and they
have an actual balance sheet. So they
can go to the credit market and being
like hey guys I have you know you you
build a gigawatt you can make you know
your margin not a crazy margin but you
can make a good margin and I now have
all this compute and now Meta and SpaceX
have this optionality of looking around
and being like is my internal use case
going to make me more money or should I
go out there and sell it to anthropic
open AAI at crazy margins. Yeah. So now
we've sort of entered a regime where um
SpaceX and Meta are saying actually I'm
going to build the compute and I can
start to rent it out for not 13. I can
sell it for 25 50 and more.
>> So as I've been doing video essays and
other formats I've been looking to hire
a new editor for the podcast. But
actively searching for editors has been
quite timeconuming because the vast
majority of candidates don't fit the
profile that I'm looking for. So I
created a recruiter in Grockbot to see
if it would help. I gave it a huge
contact dump where I monologued
basically everything that I wanted and
then it spun up four other bots to
narrow in on different parts of the
search. One went through the last year
of my email for relevant inbound. One
searched my ex feed and DMs. One went
through the end credits on various
documentaries I like. And the last one
looked for editors who work for some of
the YouTubers that I follow. Grogbot
then took all these different candidates
that these sub agents had found. It
filtered them against my criteria and
then delivered for me a final short list
to review.
>> [music]
>> To be honest, the first batch had a few
good candidates I wanted to see, but
mainly a bunch of duds. But after I gave
Grockbot some more feedback about what
it was missing, it came back with a new
list of candidates that I'm actually
extremely excited about. I ended up
saving this whole workflow as a routine.
So, every week now, Grockbot checks my
inbound email and XDMs for promising new
candidates to potentially interview. If
you want to try Grockbot yourself, go to
x.ai/bot.
What do you think their revenue per
gigawatt is by the end of 2027? like for
anthropic or open AI by end.
>> I think I think it's highly dependent on
who has the best model if they're
allowed to keep releasing their best
models. But I don't see why it wouldn't
be 50 plus million dollars a megawatt
>> by end of 27.
>> Oh, by the end of 27.
>> Um that's where it gets more
challenging. But I think I think it
could get to you know higher than that.
It's like 70 80 million a megawatt uh
blended across the company
>> if not higher.
>> Yeah. And so I think
>> if if that's the case, right, then what
happens to the price of compute? Well,
if I'm anthropic, incremental comput is
worth it. Maybe I spend $40 million a
megawatt on SpaceX compute. Um, and if
I'm SpaceX, you know, I I look to the
supply chain. I'm like, well, you know,
I've struck this deal with Jensen where
he's now all of a sudden using Twitter.
[laughter] Um, and and you know, there's
Elon saying they're exclusive to Nvidia,
but why doesn't Jensen raise his prices?
And then, you know, SKH and Micron and
Samsung looked at Nvidia like well, why
don't they raise their price? So I think
I think the value capture there's a bull
whip effect here right where uh just
because someone has risen the prices
doesn't mean the entire supply chain
rebalances immediately but over time the
supply chain will rebalance and things
will cost more and more and you know to
get that incremental capacity you sort
of have to right so TSMC raising prices
very slowly but memory companies raising
prices very quickly you know substrate
companies raising prices very quickly
different parts of the supply chain
raised you know Elon wouldn't have sold
if it was 15 but he's selling because
it's 25 Plus, so obviously he rose his
prices really quickly.
>> Yeah. I I'm sort of surprised you think
like revenue per gigawatt doesn't
increase way more than even like 100 per
>> by the end of next year.
>> When when does RSI happen? When does
take off, right? I think I think
>> even if RSI doesn't happen, the current
rate of progress continues. If you just
look at how much progress have you made
in let's say the last year and a half
like what was a model from a year and a
half ago? Let's say like
>> my problem with this is the best model
that exists in the world was trained in
February.
>> Okay. You're saying maybe we just won't
be able to release the
>> open says they're not training models
for two weeks, man. What the hell?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean there's another
there's one thing like internally are
they getting enough use for it to so
they'll like bid up the price of
computer or another is like does AI
progress as a whole slow down because of
regulation?
>> Yeah. But they're not even allowed to
use this like new model intern like
Astro is not widely deployed internally
even.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But still I don't know just
like you go if you have like a model
that is what was a model released like
let's say the beginning of last year
like GPT
>> 40. Is that 40?
>> Yeah. That that's like you're talking
about a 40 to Fable size or Mythos 2
size leap by this point uh again by the
end of 2027.
>> Yeah, but Mythos 2 is not out.
>> Yeah. Or like even Mythos, right? Like
that leap again.
>> Even Mythos is not allowed to be out,
right? They've neutered it.
>> Yeah.
>> Like we can't we can't use it to
optimize inference performance or we
can't use it to optimize all sorts of
things,
>> right? Yeah. Maybe there's like some
slowdown in AI progress or the
deployment of AI that means that the
revenue per gigawatt can be lower. But I
that that's the only way I could see it
being only 100 per megawatt by the end
of next year.
>> Yeah. I mean, as as long as the the
model gets better, the value generated
out of it gets better, obviously, who
captures the value is still up for
debate, but ultimately everyone's going
to raise their prices
>> because they can. And it's super
inflationary, especially if the method
of regulation is right now, so far it's
just don't release the models. But more
and more the method of regulation is New
York's banning data centers. Texas is
holding me moratoriums. Ohio's saying
you have to or at least trying to say
you have to like pay everyone's property
tax in a certain radius. Um these sorts
of things are going to decrease supply
and increase cost and that's going to
get passed on as well. So you start to
end up in a spot where um progress does
slow at least in the external sense. Um
even if the models internally keep
getting better and better. I I I see no
reason why like you know again like in a
in a takeoff scenario why would
Anthropic not have their best model six
months ahead of what is externally
available because of safety and
regulation but also you know the
competitive advantage. Um and then that
six-month difference if progress in
accelerates is actually a bigger um
differential. So so that's the thing
that would cap revenue per megawatt
gains to a much lower growth than we've
seen in the first half this year. Here's
something I'm very interested in. As
these companies go public and they're
accountable to investors and they let's
say end of next year they have I don't
know close to 20 gawatt. So like 10% of
their compute 2 gawatt
let's say they want to go from 60%
compute to um training to 70% compute to
training. And their investors are like
well if you're be able to generate a
hundred billion dollars per gigawatt.
you're basically saying no to like $200
billion dollars of revenue in order to
increase your training compute. As
investors are like, "What the
You're already spending so much on
training. Why are you spending even more
on training?" As a public company, do
you think Yeah. What do you think would
happen if they're just like, "No, we
will keep increasing the share of
compute we spent on training to offset
the increase in revenue that each
gigawatt of comput is giving us."
>> Yeah. So, so this is sort of what I I
personally believe that the labs are
going to allocate less and less compute
to inference over time, which I think is
very non-conensus, right? Everyone's
sort of
>> the standard belief of most people is,
oh, most compute will go to inference.
Um, most of it will go to forward passes
for training, not maybe necessarily
revenue generating inference, but
ultimately you end up with if they're
generating, you know, 30 $40 million per
megawatt today, you allocate 40% to
inference. If you now get to jo
generating 60 $70 million per megawatt,
do you still allocate 40% to inference
and generate all this profit and then do
dividends and share buybacks or do you
go build AGI? And I think the obvious
answer from Anthropic and OpenAI and not
just at the executive level but also
their board is go build AGI because it's
way more profitable, right? Um and and
so ultimately you're going to see them
ratchet up their percentage of compute
dedicated to training
>> while each increment of compute is
getting more and more profit generating
if they had dedicated to inference
>> right and and so the the whole point is
well okay if I'm gener if I'm selling
tokens is enthrop is openai releasing
ultra fast mode for just external or
they doing it internally too and it
turns out no actually I'm going to
allocate it to internal and external
because my internal, you know, value
that I'm generating from super fast AI
or the best AI model is way more than
what someone externally is.
>> And so ultimately, sure, I could
generate $100 million per megawatt, but
if I turn that towards AI research, what
is the incremental progress that I get?
And then what does that do towards my
future earnings potential, the
discounted cash flows of whatever the
hell I've done, right? Um and so you
know they're not going through that
calculation but ultimately it's it it
makes more sense to dedicate more and
more compute internally and the only
reason to in you know have inference
compute be so large is so you can grow
your training fleet.
>> Right. Right. Right. I think this is an
interesting economics question that I
feel like we can have the models digest
of what is the at what what would have
to be true about a world where they
reduce fraction of comput spend on
inference.
>> I think they have been over the last
three months already.
>> Interesting. I think I think at parts of
this year they were increasing fraction
of compute. So let's let's just take
month by month. You would agree that
every month Anthropic has added more
compute than the prior month. There
might be some noise when they like sign
a SpaceX deal or whatever, but in
general the amount of compute is is a
curve up and so in January they added
less compute than December. And yet
their revenue ads, you know, skyrocketed
and then they've plat, you know, sort of
plateaued. They're only adding, you
know, they're not adding $25 billion of
ARR every month now. And so that means
the marginal megawatt they're getting is
going higher percentage to R&D than it
is inference.
>> Yeah.
>> And so they are factually increasing
their compute towards R&D today.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think this this is like
self-evident um if you if you like look
at what they're doing enough.
>> Yeah. So I if I look at the numbers you
said of like how fast world compute
grows here here are some things I want
to understand. So it seems like if I add
up the numbers you just said it would be
over 200 gawatts of world compute by the
end of 2028, right?
>> Yeah, globally.
>> Okay. And uh how fast can that continue
growing like global global AI compute
after 2028?
>> Yeah. So 30 this year, 50 next year, 70
and 28. Um 29 should be like on the
order of 90 to 100
>> like then just 100 more every single
year or something.
>> I think I think the the slope could
continue to go upwards. I mean it's hard
to predict anything more than four years
out given uh
>> who knows what you know are we an RSI
regime or you know when is the world
economy growing at 10% a year uh because
if you're at 100 plus gigawatts a year
you're you're at absurd revenue uh uh
GDP growth
>> right if you think there's 200 gawatts
globally in 2028 how much is in China by
that point and how does like yeah how
does Chinese compute continue increasing
through this whole trend because if if
the RSI stuff kicks off in the west
before China has a large amount of
compute and maybe we're living in a
different world than when it doesn't.
>> Yeah. So, China today um so if we if we
sort of level set back to 2022, the US
was adding about 45 to 50% of the
world's compute. China was adding about
30 to 35% of the world's compute and the
rest being taken up by the rest of the
world. Since 2022, we've had big
regulations against China. um and a
dramatic increase in America. So today
70% of watts are being deployed in
America and and and you know China is is
really uh a very small number. It's sub
10% of watts being deployed for data
center AI compute is in China. Um and as
we step forward they're still at a very
small number. Um their domestic
production is quite small. Their
purchasing from Nvidia is still quite
small. Um and a lot of that ends up in
in other places as well, right? You
know, Malaysia or what have you. Um so
ultimately, China domestically still
continues to have 10 sub 10% of
incremental new compute. So in 2028
might start to inflect up, I think. Um
but it's pretty easy to say China will
have like 30 gawatts of AI compute or
less
>> by 2028.
>> Yeah, in 2028.
>> Okay. And then how fast does their
hockey stick go up?
>> I I do think in 2028 they have a big
uplift in what compute they're able to
deploy. 2026, they're still mostly
relying on a lot of the smuggled chips.
Um, you know, you know, a lot of the
chips that uh TSMC made uh for companies
that they thought weren't Huawei but
ended up being Huawei or a lot of HBM
that Samsung is shipping, you know, sort
of. But in 27, fabs start to go up in 28
especially. Fabs start to go up from
SMIC and CXMT and such where domestic
production is actually reaching many
millions of units a year. And now
they're incrementally adding, you know,
510 gigawatts in just 2028 of
domestically produced chips. Those chips
are definitely worse than the chips that
Nvidia will have in 28 or Google will
have in 28 or OpenAI will have in 2028.
>> So even even the gigawatt number
overstates things you're saying like
it's like 30 gawatt, but it's really
much worse chips. But then how Yeah. How
does it if you think the world is going
to add 100 gigawatts the following year
or some you know I know you said you
can't really say that far out how much
is China able to add the subsequent year
basically I want to know did they just
hockey stick at the point at which they
are able to start shipping large amounts
of compute or is it still going to be
less than US plus allies
>> um there's a lot left to you know
whether or not the US passes the match
act um whether or not ex tools continue
to get export controlled how fast China
can build their new equipment that
they're starting to be able to do
produce domestically. Um, but
ultimately, you know, China China is
definitely going to hockey stick if
there's anything uh China's really good
at is is scaling manufacturing really
really quickly. Um and you know I
imagine you know China's China will
start to be able to extract more and
more purchasing of even foreign chips um
into into domestic China or at least uh
close the gap in what the US is allowing
the uh you know Nvidia to sell them or
what have you.
>> But do you think China could do adding
50 gawatts by 2029 marginal incremental
gigawatts in 2029?
>> I think that's I think that's completely
reasonable. Yeah. Um, and part of that
could also be purchased from foreign.
>> Um, but yeah, I think it's completely
reasonable that China in 2029 could do
50 gigs. Um, but if most of those are
domestic chips, there is some factor
there where that 50 gawatts is really
worth as much as 20 gawatts in America
or in from from American chips.
>> Right. Right. Right. So yeah, you're
you're actually projecting a world where
maybe the leading lab in 2028 has more
compute than China will have in like all
of China will have in 29 or even 30. If
you if you weighed gigawatts by their
quality,
>> implying that there's nothing done to
slow down the US labs, right? Clearly
the government is starting and
politicians are starting to do that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Whereas China is not going to slow down
AI. In fact, the only thing they're
going to do is accelerate it. So
honestly I when I interviewed Jensen and
asked about expert controls I am a
libertarian person and I'm like I wasn't
like genuinely sure what I thought about
this issue. I was steel manning what I
what is like the opposite view that he
has and because I think it's important
to hash out ideas. Um but I'm like yeah
maybe there's a world where if we just
cooperated with China it would be better
for us especially since they control so
much of the supply chain and the other
things that will be needed for robotics
and other things. Um, but I didn't
realize the comput situation was as
as you're saying. Like actually
the export controls do seem to have like
really if if they ship the amount that
you're saying, that's a huge difference.
By the time we have automated coder and
getting into like automated researcher,
China is like way far behind on the
compute stock. And so if if that ends up
being the case, that would have worked.
I think that's actually a notable
success.
>> Um, I would say the only caveat there is
some of it is export controls. Um, but
some of it is also just uh financial
systems, right? American financial
systems are more willing to yolo into
startups than Chinese financial systems.
But once Chinese financial systems
choose an industry to focus on, they'll
subsidize it a hell of a lot more.
>> Um, and so the Chinese semiconductor
industry has significantly more
subsidies than the rest of the world's
semiconductor industries combined. um
which which points to like you know if
takeoff is not as fast as sort of you're
implying but actually takes longer then
ultimately China will catch up
drastically on the semiconductor side
which then is compute at some point. The
other aspect of this that I would think
is like I think is like noteworthy is um
Chinese companies today are not that far
behind in AI models at least perceivably
by the public uh relative to the amount
of compute they have right the leading
Chinese labs have 100 200 megawatts
total of compute at most um bite dance
uh seed seed being the one outlier where
they have significantly more than that
um but you know Kimmy is not running you
know a gigawatt or anywhere close to it.
Yeah.
>> Um whereas anthropic is you know nearly
5 gawatt by the end of the year right or
more sorry. Um and so you know the
question is sort of well does it matter?
And I think right now it doesn't matter
that much the this difference in compute
because you know when we break down the
compute ratio or budget of a lab
historically it's um been you know let's
say 60 or so far it's been like 60%
training 40% inference but that training
gets broken down further and it's
actually like 50% of the compute is
research like 10% of the compute is
development and then 40% is inference
and what I mean by research and
development is you know research
Researchers are generating ideas,
testing new architectures, testing new
data mixes, testing new hyperparameters,
whatever it is they're doing, new
attention techniques, blah blah blah.
But ultimately when they do the training
run, when Enthropic trains mythos, it's
sub 200 megawatts, right?
>> The pre-train or the whole thing?
>> The pre-train.
>> Um, it's sub 200 megawatts for call it
two months. Um, and then the RL is even
less.
>> But you think the RL was less to compute
than the pre-train?
>> Uh, at least in terms of uh single sight
inference, I mean single sight of
pre-training. Yeah,
>> but total computer was probably higher,
right?
>> Total, but it's like sequential, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, at most the most they ever used at
one point in time was maybe 200
megawatt.
>> Mhm.
>> And then in reality, they had multiple
gigawatts. So, most of their compute was
going to the research, not the
development of a model. And there's
reasons for this, right? You can't it's
hard to coordinate all these clusters.
It's hard to um colllocate all of them.
It's hard to do multi-sight training.
it's hard to do um RL, you know,
generating even more rollouts during RL
does not necessarily make it better.
There's all sorts of reasons why you may
not be able to leverage, you know, all 2
gigawatts that you have for training
onto training, right? Actually, I can
only leverage 200 megawatts. As we get
closer and as we get further and further
down implement automated coding,
automated researcher, I actually expect
the percentage of the compute budget
that goes to research versus training to
start to and uh to start to like become
a lot more fuzzy or even higher for
training. Um also things like continual
learning, right? All of these things
start to mean that more and more is
actually going to training the model. So
you have if you end up in a world where
you're doing 100 gigawatts a year at
current prices that would be five
trillion of capex every single year
>> and then stack on the fact that you have
to build the power plants way before
then slash it's a 30-year asset. You
stack on the fact that the data centers
are you know 15 20 year asset and you
have to build that then too. So the 5
trillion you know you have to account
for future years growth so it's actually
going to be more like seven or 10
trillion
>> huh of capex. I don't understand because
you're not including the fact that like
that doesn't include the fact that
there's not the infrastructure for the
power uh generation or whatever in the
data center itself,
>> right? Exactly. Um and and the data
center itself is um
when when you talk about AI capex,
people are saying 4050 billion, but
that's really just the critical IT.
Yeah.
>> Right. The servers, the networking, the
fiber, the transceivers, optical
communications, all this sort of stuff.
um it doesn't account for the data
center itself
>> or the power plants themselves which are
being built ahead of time.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> if I'm building 100 gawatts this year
and 150 gawatts next year, well then all
of the buildings for that 150 gawatts
need to be built and capex this year.
And if I'm building 200 gawatts the year
after that, all those power plants need
to be spent. You have to buy the
turbines this year,
>> right? And so you've got this like l
this like actually it's much bigger than
even $5 trillion if you're building uh
100 gigawatts,
>> right? So very plausibly incremental
capex every year is
getting close to 10 trillion dollars
>> by the end of the decade
>> right which is going to be like close to
a tenth of the world economy and like a
third of if all of it's going up in the
US it's like well the US economy will
have grown as well but still in the
current size of the US economy it'll be
like a third to a quarter of the US
economy would just be going towards data
centers and as I say that out loud I'm
like maybe maybe you're right and we
just won't allow it and that's the
reason this doesn't happen right cuz
like for this exponential to continue
just like a quarter of the world a
quarter of America's economy is just
building data centers
>> yeah I mean I believe in capitalism and
reallocation of resources towards the
most profitable thing but at the same
time politics exist
>> um and credit markets exist and capital
markets exist so to enable let's say
that 100 gawatts by 2030 or let's even
like let's even like pare it down to
2028 where it's like three or four
trillion dollars of capex across all of
these items uh you know a couple you
know over you know two and a half
towards comput uh IT capex and then
another one to two on data center and
energy um and all the supply chain
downstream like semiconductors and all
that stuff so if you're at if you're at
three or four trillion dollars of capex
where does all this cash come from no
one is generating that much cash from
the business yet right um hyperscalers
they funded all of the growth up until
now Google Microsoft Amazon uh Meta they
funded a huge percentage of it they were
more than half of compute but they now
don't generate cash they actually spend
everything on capex and in addition they
raise debt and spend everything on capex
right you've seen meta do it even Amazon
even Google um you know Microsoft will
be there soon everyone is raising debt
to pay for their capex so now who is the
incremental person to pay for this um
that was not doing it before in the case
of like Google it was pretty simple for
them to stop doing buybacks or meta stop
doing buybacks and turn around and buy
computer infrastruure structure and that
doesn't have a huge effect on the market
um but it does have some effect. But as
you as you step forward to 2028 where
the hyperscalers are now raising
hundreds of billions of dollars of debt
um and then all of their supply chain is
raising hundreds of billions of dollars
of debt who pays for this and so there's
a few different ways um you know there's
the semiconductor companies like Nvidia
uh and Broadcom and the memory companies
turning around and deciding to fund some
of this capex. There's the traditional
infrastructure investors who are turning
around and gathering capital and
investing in infrastructure and instead
of bridges, it's data centers. Um, and
then lastly, there's everyone in the
economy who's realizing maybe I
shouldn't buy a home or maybe I
shouldn't invest in credit for a home
that's helping people buy homes or maybe
I shouldn't buy government debt. I
should just buy hyperscaler debt or I
should just buy this data centers debt
or I should buy enthropics debt because
Enthropic is willing to pay 20%
uh you know rates for you know the
incremental billion dollars to build
their capacity because they know their
revenue from it's going to be huge and
they're going to pay 20% because it's
still better than renting it from SpaceX
for $50 billion a gigawatt. Um so you
you've got all of this contention but if
you now do this the whole world economy
is like really shifted around.
Antithesis is a deterministic software
testing platform that enables perfect
reproducibility. It also unlocks some
pretty insane approaches to debugging
like time travel. With antithesis,
[music] you can jump to any point in the
trajectory and start from there. So when
there's a crash, you can rewind to the
exact moment that something went wrong
and freeze the entire system, the
application, the database, even the
environment itself. This lets you do
something that would otherwise be
impossible, which is to observe every
part of a distributed system at the
exact same instant. Time travel also
allows you to add telemetry and logging
to an event that has already happened.
For example, you can rewind to 5 seconds
before a crash and decide to capture all
the network traffic. Most powerfully,
antithesis gives you a live terminal
into your system that you can use to
perturb anything you wish. Kill a node
or disable a feature and then hit play
and see what happens. then go back and
try something else. In production, you
often only get one shot on goal with
this sort of destructive analysis. If
you restart a deadlock service, for
example, the exact deadlock you needed
to study disappears. But with
antithesis, the original timeline is
always reproducible. So you can test as
many hypotheses as [music] you need. And
if you don't want to do all this time
traveling yourself, you can just have
your agents do it for you via the
antithesis API. Go to
antithesis.com/warcash [music]
to learn more.
So you and I have been debating uh off
air for the last few days whether there
will be a sovereign debt crisis as a
result of AI. And the logic is this. Um
AI is you you have a situation where as
we were mentioning very little
investment turns into a lot of money
right so the rate of return
>> what a problem dude oh my god
[laughter]
can't believe it.
No, it is a huge problem for everybody
else who can't turn a little money into
a lot of money, right? Um, so the rate
of return is incredibly high. Even at
the data center level, you know, if you
build if you like build a data center
and you're like give rent out to
anthropic or urban AI for like 10x what
it cost you on a depreciated basis to
build it, it's crazy. Um, and so
you turn $1 into like $2 or $10 or
something at the end of the year. That
raises the rate of interest higher. Now
if the rate of interest goes higher and
if it does that for the entire economy
and people are borrowing more and more
money they're competing against the
other lending that the government would
have done or that other companies would
have done or that you as a consumer or a
mortgage buyer would have done. Uh then
that's just making it basically more
expensive for everybody else to borrow.
This has huge implications for tons and
tons of people. Sorry, I'm going to go
on a bit of a monologue here. Um but we
we we've been thinking about this
together. So I think the US will be fine
at the end of the day because they can
if the data centers are built in
America, we can fundamentally just like
tax the data centers. But the way the
current tax system is set up, you know,
corporate income is like less than 10%
of federal revenues and 80% plus is
payroll taxes and income taxes which as
more and more automation happens will
shrink. Um at the same time on the
spending side currently 20% of tax
revenue spending goes towards paying
servicing the debt basically paying
interest payments on the debt. Um now a
lot of the debt is short duration so it
refurbishes every 5 years it rolls over.
Why why are you laughing?
[laughter]
>> Cuz you know it's [clears throat] like
things we've learn you've learned in the
last
[laughter]
>> Yeah. like it's any different for you.
>> Like you got a degree in
financial economics.
>> I didn't [laughter] I didn't
>> The internet thinks I'm a beekeeper.
>> Few months. Few months. Few months.
>> Um [laughter]
this is our business. Dylan,
sorry. Sorry. Um [laughter]
and uh so
now I'm self-conscious.
>> No, it's good. You're doing good. I just
think it's [laughter] funny.
million people listen to this guy who
just learned about death this month.
[laughter]
>> Um so you go from 20% of is suppose
interest rates rise uh 1%. Then the um
over a 5year basis the amount of the
fraction of tax revenue that goes
towards servicing the debt basically
goes from 20% to 25%. If they rise five
percentages that would go towards like
north of 40%. But if you take into
account the fact that the government is
borrowing $2 trillion every single year,
then that goes from like 40% to like
north of 60%. So 60% of tax revenue
basically just goes towards paying
interest payments on the debt. Now I
think the US is going to be fine because
also the tax base will increase if we
let data centers get built in America.
Um other countries are absolutely
in my opinion. I was just looking at
which countries have a lot of debt, have
very little tax revenue and also a lot
of their debt is serviced quite often
and those countries like Pakistan or
Nigeria or something I think are just
going to be very in this new
interest rate regime.
>> So, so, so this this this crowding out
effect is actually like the thing that
I've like is the reason it's not like
yolo 1 billion gigawatts. Yeah.
>> Right. Um, you've got you've got all
these industries and countries that use
a lot of debt, whether it's, you know,
all these impoverished countries that
you mentioned earlier that are just
going to default. You've got like
consumer packaged goods, right? Like all
of these like companies that make things
you see at Trader Joe's or wherever
use a lot of debt. All these telecom
companies use a lot of debt and banks
use a lot of debt. And so if interest
rates go up um in the market, not
necessarily the government set interest
rate, but in the market, the spread of
interest rate uh between what the
government says their federal rate is
versus what everyone else is charging
because Amazon wants to raise a hundred
billion dollars of debt next year or
whatever the hell the number is. Um you
know, probably less, but um you end up
with this like really challenging
problem of where does the cash come
from? um there is some level that is
funded by cash flows and cash flows keep
going up but the logical thing to do is
to invest way more than your cash flows
because then the returns in the future
years will be amazing. So, you have this
delta. Um, and then what's pushing down
on the delta is all of these other
things, right? There's regulations
against data centers, regulations, uh,
you know, consumers getting mad, uh,
politicians getting mad, regulations
against AI, um, the AI labs not
releasing their latest models because of
safety reasons. Um, all of these things
and and and interest rates going up um
are are are an influence on all of these
things. So all of these things bend the
curve from what does capitalism want in
terms of just pure simple economics to
what does the complex system that we
have want and bends it lower and lower
and lower to where not as many gigawatts
as should be built will be built.
>> Well the interest rate is part of
capitalism right?
>> Yeah but like you know like in the
simple economic model versus like the
more complex what we have.
>> Yeah. Um what is the rate at which you
think Amazon or Anthropic or whatever
will be releasing bonds for debt next
year? They do hundreds of billions of
dollars of debt. What is the rate? What
is the average rate?
>> I I don't think Amazon will do hundreds
of billions of dollars of debt
>> to total. Let's say the big
>> the hyperscalers in total will raise and
and all the clouds in in the modeling
that we do, we have about 11 trillion of
capex from 2024 to 2029
>> total
>> total. And if you do, you know, if you
fund a lot of this with cash flows and
as much as you can, you still end up
with north of $5 trillion of credit that
need to be issued for this 11 trillion
plus.
>> You don't think the AI revenue continues
even 3xing year over year?
>> AI revenue does go up. I don't think it
can go up forever. I don't you know like
just like w without like certain
constraints being hit. I think c labs
will have certain incentives. Um and and
labs are not the ones building all the
compute in many cases even though
they're increasingly trying to go that
way.
>> They'll have all these cash flow like if
their revenue keeps incre whatever
that's fine but if you how much would
you say the revenue will be
>> you think they'll not have that much
revenue.
>> No I'm just saying till 2029 there's you
know something on the order of 11
trillion of capex
>> and six of that is funded with cash and
five of that is funded with debt. Um,
and if that's the case, $5 trillion of
debt being raised across the whole
ecosystem does make interest rates go
up. And then what prevents that? You
know, there's a couple things. One, do
labs increase their revenue per megawatt
more and keep inference allocations
large, in which case they're taking all
this profit. They're accumulating all
the profit across the S&P 500 because
everyone's paying to, you know, reduce
their costs. Um, of course, their
profits will also go up, but um, you
know, cash has to come from somewhere.
Um, so there's an upper limit on how
fast their revenue can grow versus the
value they deliver into the world. And
there's a diffusion aspect of the
technology. Um, but ultimately labs
revenue keep going up. They can't cash
flow fund everything. The optimal
scenario is you actually use credit as
much as you can to fund because even if
cash flows from the labs fund a lot of
stuff, you want to build more than that.
>> Um, and so there is some amount of
credit that gets built. Our current
modeling has $5 trillion of credit and
$6 trillion of cash funded
infrastructure investments through 29.
Um, and when you take that, you you've
sort of got, you know, this is not
enough compute relative to what this
demand growth is from the AI models. And
so you've got the obvious answer, which
is revenue per megawatt keeps going up.
>> Yeah, that that makes sense. So, how
much do you think interest rates will
increase by 2029 as a result of all
this? Dude, you know, it's just vibing a
number. But if you're vibing a number
out, you know, growth in the world and
economy is growing up a lot. So why
wouldn't interest rates y
>> for Amazon go from, you know, from where
they are today? Um I think Meta pay
Okay, let's like So this is going to be
extremely vibed out, but recently Meta's
raised at like 5 to 6%. I don't see why
they wouldn't pay 8%. because they would
happily pay 8% because the return from
the compute that they're going to build
is humongous, right? Um and the market
won't want them to, but if they they
they'll want to pay 8%. The flip side is
if they pay 8%.
>> versus the five they do, five and a
half, six they do today, you know, 250
bips increase,
>> that makes everyone else in the economy
also pay 250 bips more.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Which then causes a lot of things,
right? banks will scream because if
their credit spread goes up, then their
assets don't rep their their uh their
debt themselves reprices faster than
their assets repric. Um and you
ultimately end up with they're losing
tons of money if their credit spread
blows up.
>> The other consequences of this are
>> this is a point you made but the if
interest rates rise the discount rate
increases which means that the discount
cash flows of all equities
>> Yeah. crater which means that even
though the stock market as a whole might
be doing fine like S&P 500 will be fine
>> any individual stock will probably have
just like cratered in value especially
the um the Buffett like Berkshire type
you know pay good cash flows for 30 year
type
>> yeah it's like it's like why would I pay
this much for you know um you know
Johnson and Johnson
>> right
>> who you know like they're they're seen
as a stable stock good cash flows
they'll return their cash flows over
time or a railway company like why the
would I invest that much if my
discount rate isn't 3% or 5% it's now 8%
or 10%
>> and and and for developing countries
what's there Basil Hopper who's a good
friend and he's an economist he um made
this point that we'll see a second
vulker shock so in the 80s to fight
inflation uh Fed chair Paul Vulker
raised interest rates like more than 5%
um or it's like something like 8% uh
real interest rates 8% and that caused
some 40 different countries, mostly
Latin America, to default in that
decade. And I think that will probably
happen again. In fact, okay, now we're
getting into like singularity talk. So,
we're even talking about what happens if
interest
>> I think this all happens before
singularity.
>> Yeah, that's what I'm saying. That's
what I'm saying. So, we were talking
about like, you know, before
singularity, interest rates rise 2%, 3%,
etc. At some point, I think it's very
likely that the world economy will be
doubling every single year.
Okay, this is not happening in five
years, but it'll happen eventually. It
just like there will be there's this uh
there's a researcher Damon Binder who's
done great work on this, but basically
if you look at like input output tables
in a fully automated economy, just like
what would it take to like double the
entire stock of things in the economy
ever?
>> If [laughter]
economy grows at 3% a year, then it's
like, you know, rule of 70, it's like 20
something years,
>> right? But then but he was like okay
well right now we're bottlenecked by the
fact that there's people and you can't
like double people every single year but
in a world where like you can also
double labor force every single year how
fast can the economy grow and I think it
could double every single year at the
very least would be like tens of percent
every single year. Okay the rate of
interest should be pretty close to the
growth rate. It won't be exactly that
because of consumption but it should it
should be pretty similar. So then we'll
go into a world I think in the 2030s
where the rate of interest is like tens
of percent. Um, and like I I don't know,
part of my brain is like it might be
hundreds of percent, but like okay,
let's say it's at least tens of percent.
I'm just like, okay, every country that
is not involved in the production of AI
defaults. Um, every stock that is not an
AI stock is like worth basically zero
because discounted cash flows are worth
nothing. If the federal government can't
figure out a way to tax AI, you know,
the the servicing the debt is more than
the current uh tax revenue. um all these
other effects that I'm sure we're not
even pricing in like you can't get a
mortgage etc etc off because
fundamentally what is happening in this
world like this is all nerd speak right
but like let's step back what's h
happening
>> just now it started the nerd speech
[laughter]
>> we'd be entering a regime we're just
we're in a totally different growth
regime basically and the economy is
basically saying hey you like paying
people you bar the government borrowing
money to pay people pensions the
opportunity cost of that is extremely
high now because that money could be
spent building a robot factory that
builds a robot factory that builds a
robot factory and so the opportunity
cost of capital is going to increase a
ton and that just like that's
fundamentally what the cause of all of
these things we're talking about.
>> Yeah. So, so as interest rates go up,
equity markets get pummeled. Yeah.
>> Um and even AI companies, right? People
are like, you know, some people who
really believe in AI are like, why does
Micron or Heinex or Kyia trade at two or
three times earnings? And it's like,
well, if you're really AIP, everything
in the economy should trade at like two
or three times earnings.
>> Um, and if you're not AID, then sure,
they're they're over earning. Um, so
it's sort of like a an argument for why
like I think memory is going to do
great, but you know, memory memory
stocks shouldn't, you know, 10x or
whatever again because if they were if
we're in the market where there's that
much demand for memory, which means AI's
caused this drastic change in the
economy, then everything should trade at
like two or 3x multiples and the stock
market should crash. Right.
>> Right. And so in a sense, like Meta
trading at I don't know, I think Meta
trades at like some they're like $1.5
trillion company. It's like what silly?
Um, they're worth way more than that, at
least in like a logical sense. you just
look at their cash flows and and like
all the infrastructure they're hoarding
and all the compute that they're going
to be able to sell for crazy amounts of
uh dollars per watt either as tokens
because their lab works or just
anthropic and open AI um ultimately
becomes a question of like you have to
reallocate all the capital to the AGI
and you do that by pricing everyone else
out and and and so the limiter on AGI is
not how fast can the research engineers
like you know our roommate Shoto can
crank the gear It's actually just like
how much does the rest of the world let
that happen, right? Because they're
going to regulate. They're going to
obviously increase interest rates.
They're going to say no data centers.
They're going to say stop building fabs.
They're going to say, oh every
company's equity value is tanking, so
how can I pay for AI,
you know, to increase my business? Well,
then, you know, like, okay, then open
have to start like building their own
stuff. And obviously they're going to
eventually focus, you know, they're
building their own chips already or at
least designing their own chips and
it'll expand out. They're, you know,
they're contracting their own data
centers and building their own uh infra
in the next couple years. Um, you know,
there there's sort of like how does this
reallocation of the economy happen? But
there's a lot of downward pressure on it
not being, you know, just straight
takeoff. um even if the models were
capable of it uh which which I think you
and I believe we're in a world where
models are capable of that but slow
takeoff is is at least my hope possible
because everything in the economy and
and regulatory world like government
saying don't release your models
government saying actually you can't
even use your models internally that
much because that's going to happen soon
they're already saying you can't release
your models
>> which is actually the thing I'm most
worried about is you know a singularity
which external deployment is is actually
helping, right? So, the fact that we're
preventing external deployment.
>> Well, does that does that prevent
singularity?
>> I mean, right now it would lead to more
revenue because the models are on
capable of RSI, but I'm worried about a
world where it's 2030 and the
government's like, "We're going to wait
6 months before you can release your
model to the public."
>> 6 months, 100x, let's go.
>> Yeah. And in that six months, they're
just like they do like recursive self-
improvement internally. They just have
all kinds of crazy happening in the
company. Meanwhile, the rest of us are
stuck with models that are like at
current pace years behind. Yeah.
>> So, here's my thought. Okay. Suppose
that the whole world gets in on this
conspiracy to like try to slow down AI.
>> I don't think it's a conspiracy. It's
like it's outwardly written, you know,
from like every politician.
>> Suppose they basically prevent an entire
they slow down AI by a year. They if
comput is increasing two to 3x every
single year. They prevent a whole year
of AI deployment such that you're a year
behind where you would otherwise been.
During um RSI, you're getting 3 to six
years of AI progress in a single year.
>> But but they can't they don't just limit
compute, right? They also limit the
lab's ability to release the model
internally, right? We saw that had to
stop giving Mythos to foreign employees
for a bit.
>> I didn't I didn't know that was true.
Like internally as well.
>> I mean that's what they claimed. And
they
>> I thought that was just a different
checkpoint that was not mythos, but it
was basically Mythos.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But I mean like stuff like
that is not going to be allowed either,
right? Like the government is dumb, but
they're not that dumb, right? Like you
know, I I would hope at least. Um, you
know, governments are going to not want
companies, at least the US government
has the cards here, is not going to want
Anthropic to use methos for internally.
They're going to be like, hold the
on, right? Like, slow down, you know,
cuz cuz all of these regulatory reasons,
everyone who's elected is going to hate
AI. Even the people who are elected
already hate AI. um all the constituents
you're going to literally have like I
bet you at some point your parents are
going to call you and be like Daresha
you're doing a terrible job you're
making every AI progress happen faster
like it's my podcast
>> it's going to happen it's going to
happen my podcast I'm accelerating
progress [laughter]
>> I mean maybe you educate people right
and and maybe if they're smarter they're
progressing AI faster but anyways like
you you're going to have real world
constraints on the progress and
development and deployment of AI even
though you It will happen eventually.
It's like we're we could tear ourselves
apart before we get there.
>> Jane Street is hiring for two separate
ML internships right now. One focused on
ML engineering and the other focused on
ML research. I sat down with Aloque who
helps run the research track to learn
more about that program. I think this
domain is fundamentally underststudied.
Often we have unanswered questions
within our deep learning research team
where we don't understand some say some
market participants behaviors or certain
dynamics of how trading happens. These
unanswered questions make for really
good intern projects cuz they are
ultimately topics that we care about and
just haven't gotten around to figuring
out yet. So even as an intern, you'll be
contributing to real research, not
working on some sort of contrived
exercise. The Jane Street team follows
Frontier LLM research closely. A
relatively common intern project is
adapting a recent paper to financial
markets which come with their own set of
gnarly problems. Ultimately, we're
trying to model thousands of
interconnected irregular time series.
The signal to noise ratios are extremely
low because we have a lot of competitors
trying to do the same. So, we have this
like adversarial non-stationary
extremely highdimensional problem that
we were trying to solve. To be clear,
you don't need to know anything about
finance in order to be a good fit. As
long as you have a background in ML
research, Jane Street can teach you the
rest. Their 2027 internship applications
are open now. Apply at
janestreet.com/bourash.
One thing I find crazy about these
scenarios is just how much of the
world's future labor supply ends up in
uh very few companies and also how fast
the labor supply grows yearover-year. So
if like computer at the frontier you
know in flop terms is growing four or 5x
a year and further the comput required
to achability is like decreasing 3x a
year. So the computer at the frontier or
the basically the effective AI
population size at the frontier labs is
increasing 10x year over year. And so
that doesn't really matter that much
right now because AIs are not good
enough to do full jobs or be like as
autonomous as people in their capacity
to do work or pull off schemes or
whatever. But if the current trend
continues, you have a world where open
AI goes from having say 10 million
basically AI laborers this year to 100
million the next year to a billion the
year after that. And then pretty soon,
even if comput scaling slows down, it
doesn't take many more years before each
company individually has more labor
equivalence than there are people on
Earth. Um, and I think that's like a
thing that is very plausible by the end
of this decade that there's more AI
labor, more effective population within
a single lab um, than there are people
on Earth. So we talk often about
centralization of power because of
nationalization or whatever but we don't
think enough about the fact that we're
actually moving very fast into a regime
where most AI labor or sorry most most
people like in terms of like the a work
output or something is just like
concentrated within two labs who are
consuming more and more of the world's
compute and so if if these AIs are
misaligned then most of the world is
misaligned basically because like most
of the world's minds are there um but
even if they're not it just very few
companies have like a lot of influence
or a lot Yeah, it's it's sort of um
there was the whole spat recently where
it's like um I think Gavin Baker was
like and Daario believes that there's
only be one company in the world and
then you know Shelto and Daario came out
and were like no no no we didn't say
that. Um but ultimately you know if you
believe in RSI you believe in the labs
are the most effective uh user of
compute and can generate the most um
value from the compute then the only
thing that's going to happen is
centralization of compute and if you
believe in you know sort of AI
researchers RSI AGI then all of this
exists all of this is the base this is
even true there's no RSI the current
effective like
>> effective population of the frontier is
currently increasing 10x year over year
for a given level of capabilities Right.
So if you get to the level of
capabilities which is a human um a very
competent remote worker or like a very
competent software engineer or very
competent researcher that population of
those would like 10x year over year at
the current rate of cap current rate of
capabilities
>> and without RSI then once you have RSI
it's
>> like maybe growing like 100x a year or
thousandx a year or they're like
intelligence is increasing but the
population isn't increasing or some
mixture of the two right. Um, yeah. I
mean, I guess I guess like what world do
you see, Dwarash, where everything is
not centralized? Um, because it seems to
me that every force is screeching
towards centralization. And that's scary
as hell.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, I don't I don't, you know, I would
love for it not to be centralized
completely. Um, but maybe that's that's
the whole point of a m a machine that
loves grace, right? Is is it is
everything and it makes our lives great.
>> Yeah. It's so hard to think about the
future. Um but I agree with you that I
think the fundamental problem is that
lab
AI training has huge economies of scale
because any effort you spend into
training an AI for a specific skill or
specific set of knowledge gets amortized
across billions of sessions or billions
of users. Um the further so that's like
one effect. The other effect is if
you're slightly ahead in the AI race and
comput is in shortage, you can charge a
much higher markoff because you can
better economize the scarce resource. So
there's like two effects which are give
more and more to the person who's like
ahead in the AI race. There may be more,
right? So if there's a models are
learning from deployment and one model
is like deployed much more widely than
another one. It's getting much more like
real world data. Yeah, your point your
point is taken that like whether it's
user deployment and continual learning
um whether it's uh training having these
economies of scales um whether it's the
incremental progress that the best AI
model helps you to make the next AI
model um RSI all of these things
>> I didn't mention RSI
>> all of these things point to
centralization
>> so I think one of the big intellectual
projects honestly um that yeah we should
spend some time thinking about uh async
or at least I'll spend some time
thinking about is what is a vision of
like a decentral centralized, broadly
empowered future after AGI that takes
these economies of scale seriously. The
alternative vision is that the
government controls it. And maybe you
think that you can trust the government
more because it's not a private
corporation.
>> I don't trust the government and I don't
trust Daario and I don't trust Z.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's the problem, right?
Um but there's no at least obviously
obviously it's like very easy to be
wrong about the future and you don't
anticipate a key effect or something
that changes everything. But Xanti, it's
very hard to see a reason why there or
like how we avoid a scenario where we
have to choose one.
>> Why capitalism worked, right? It's the
decentralized decision-making and
decentralized power and why super
centralized capitalistic economies
actually grew slower than super
decentralized capitalist economies to
some extent. You have to have rule of
law and all this,
>> but then AI flips all this on its head,
right? And ultimately you're like
actually private ownership is probably
not the most efficient economy and
therefore it grows slower than an AI
economy which is centralized. It's still
private ownership, but it's like how
many firms are really involved in this
this like the share of the economy
that's not what like 5% of the economy
or something like that in the US sorry 1
trillion divided by 30 less than that
sorry but um yeah maybe two 2% of the
economy right now it's like Nvidia is a
huge share of it and anthropic and open
AI and these hyperscalers and obviously
there's other firms involved but like a
large share of the EI stuff is just
happening from very few companies so
it's like it could be private property
but like very few companies are involved
>> I mean this is what the structure of the
market is doing so you What what can
prevent it? I don't know. I don't unless
AI progress slows down
>> unless governments regulate the out
of it. This is all that happens. In
which case, you know, we're headed for a
world where either we have super
concentration of resources and we pray
that that one company gets everything
right or we have governments slow
everything down and people slow
everything down and and you have a
slowdown of progress somehow hopefully
>> and and there is a more of a balance of
power and even as we go towards an AGI,
ASI, RSI,
>> um
>> everything along the way will still lead
to someone's going to allocate going to
capture more resources. So, so it's kind
of hard for a framework in which AI
doesn't lead to super concentration.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, the one positive thing here is that
today Anthropic does not capture most of
the value. So, we can talk all we want
about, oh, you know, they went from $20
million per megawatt to $100 million a
megawatt, but they're still paying 13 um
for a lot of the compute they're buying.
But at the end of the day, the reason
they've gone to $100 million per
megawatt is because Jane Street is
capturing $300 million per megawatt or
$500 million per megawatt. Um where
Dwares from researching his podcast and
learning about credit is capturing, you
know, how many dollars per megawatt now,
how much can you use? Tough.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um but you know, I think I think that's
the like one saving grace is that the
rest of the economy maybe profits so
much more from anthropic. No, but the
whole logic you're laying out earlier of
them reallocating inference to AI R&D,
the whole logic of that is that the uh
returns to labor inside AI labs is much
higher.
>> This is my cope.
>> Returns outside. Yeah,
>> this is my cope. I agree.
>> In in all scenarios of the world, you
know, there's 80,000 worlds and only one
of them anthropic doesn't own the whole
world. Is is that is that
>> you know, again, power concentrates
because I don't want to send the tokens
outside. They're more valuable inside.
And so it's the same thing, right? Why
would I let Jane Street, you know, make
all this money off of these degenerate
options traders?
>> Hey, they're they're a sponsor. Come on.
[laughter]
>> Jesus Christ.
>> No, I think it's great. I think it's
great. It's a good value for the world
to make it an efficient market.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. [laughter]
>> You know, Jane Street making all this
money off of getting the world view
correctly, making money off of
degenerate options traders, whatever it
is. You know, why would Anthropic
allocate compete to that if enth if if
if the end, you know, monetization that
Jane Street has per megawatt is 200. So,
they're willing to pay anthropic 100.
Well, what if Anthropic can just
generate hundreds of millions of dollars
per megawatt by using that compute
internally and that's that's what's
happening.
>> Yeah. Well, on that somber note, um I
guess I guess uh I guess we'll meet
again when the RSI is officially kicked
off. You're not [laughter] You're not
going to have me on your podcast again
for like two months.
>> All right, cool. Thanks, dude.